Evangelia ADAMOU

Senior researcher

LACITO - CNRS
7, rue Guy Moquet
94801 Villejuif - France
0033 1 49 58 37 66
adamou@vjf.cnrs.fr
http://lacito.vjf.cnrs.fr/membres/adamou.htm

(updated in August 2011)

CURRENT STATUS

Researcher (Chargée de Recherches 1ère classe), French National Center for Scientific Research (CNRS) – Oral Tradition Languages and Civilisations Laboratory (LACITO)

Assistant director of the LACITO laboratory (since 2009) [dir. F. Jacquesson]

Treasurer of the Linguistic Society of Paris (Société de linguistique de Paris) (since 2009)

1. EDUCATION

- **'Ph.D' in Linguistics,** University Paris 5, France (2001)
- 'DEA' in Linguistics, University Paris 12, France (1998)
- 'Ptychion' in French Language and Literature, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Greece (1997)
- 'Licence', Erasmus exchange, University Paris 8, France (1996)

2. ACADEMIC APPOINTMENTS

since 1 oct. 2005	Chargée de recherches, CNRS – LACITO Langues et Civilisations à Tradition Orale
2003-2004	Attachée temporaire d'enseignement et de recherche (ATER), University Paris 5
2001-2003	Chargée de cours. University Paris 5

3. RECENT RESEARCH PROJECTS

5. RECENT RESEARCH PROJECTS	
2010-2012	Electronic database of endangered Slavic varieties in non-Slavic speaking European countries (2010-2012) [Co-PIs: Evangelia Adamou & Walter Breu (U. Konstanz)] Awarding Body: French National Research Agency (ANR) & Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG)
2009-2013	Towards a multi-level, typological and computer-assisted analysis of contact-induced language change [PI: I. Léglise] Awarding Body: French National Research Agency (ANR)
2010-2012	Textual and Lexical Documentation of Ixcatec, a highly endangered Otomanguean language of Oaxaca, Mexico - Major Documentation Project [PI : D. Costaouec, Université René Descartes] Awarding Body: Endangered Languages Documentation Program
2009-2010	Lost in intonation: the interaction of intonation and meaning in the speech of L1, L2 and heritage speakers of Greek and its implications for cross-cultural communication and education [PI: Marina Terkourafi, University of Illinois] Awarding Body: Illinois-Worldwide Universities Network (WUN)

4. LANGUAGES

Native: Modern Greek Fluent: French, English Intermediate: Spanish, Italian

Studied: Literary Macedonian, Literary Bulgarian, Chinese, Arabic, Latin, Ancient Greek

Fieldwork languages: Balkan Slavic (Nashta, Pomak), Romani (Greece, Mexico), Ixcatec (Otomanguean,

Mexico)

5. LINGUISTIC FIELDWORK

Balkan Slavic, Nashta Liti, Greece. 2002 ; 2003 ; 2004

Funded by Lacito-CNRS: 2005; 2006; 2007

Funded by ANR EuroSlav2010: 2011.

Balkan Slavic, Pomak, Thrace, Greece. Funded by Lacito-CNRS :

2005; 2006; 2007; 2009

Romani, Thrace, Greece. Funded by Lacito-CNRS:

2005 - 2006 ; 2007 ; 2009 Funded by ANR Clapoty : 2010.

Armenien, Greece. Funded by Lacito-CNRS:

2005

Ixcatec, Oaxaca, Mexico. Funded by: Lacito / HRELP-ELDP 'Documentation

Romani, Oaxaca, Mexico. de l'ixcatèque'

2010;2011

6. TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2011-2012 **Introduction to Ethnolinguistics**

University Paris Descartes, Faculty of Human and Social Sciences

Licence L3 de Sciences du Langage

2008-2010 **Seminar Master II**

École des Hautes Études en Sciences Sociales, Centre d'Études byzantines, néo-

helléniques et sud-est européennes [dir. Paolo Odorico]

• The multilingual inherritance of Greece

2003-2004 **TD DEUG** University Paris 5

TD Introduction to phonetics and phonology

2001-2004 • TD Methodology of linguistics

• TD Introduction to linguistics

• TD History of linguistics

• TD French in space and time

7. PUBLICATIONS

7.1. Authored books

Adamou E., 2006, *Le nashta. Description d'un parler slave de Grèce en voie de disparition*, Muenchen, Lincom, 121 p.

7.2. Edited books

Adamou E. (éd.), 2008, *Le patrimoine plurilingue de la Grèce - Le nom des langues II*, dir. de coll. Andrée Tabouret-Keller, BCILL 121, Leuven, Peeters, 153 p.

7.3. Book introduction

Adamou E., 2008, Introduction, *Le patrimoine plurilingue de la Grèce - Le nom des langues II*, E. Adamou (éd.), BCILL 121, Leuven, Peeters, 15-30.

7.4. Chapters in edited volumes

Adamou E., submited, Ditropic cliticization in Ixcatec.

- Adamou E., in press (2011), Verb morphologies in contact: evidence from the Balkan area. In Stolz T., Vanhove M., Otsuka H. & A. Urdze (eds). *Morphologies in contact*. Berlin, Akademie Verlag, 20 p.
- Adamou E., in press (2011), Le parfait avec 'avoir' dans l'aire balkanique : approche multifactorielle et diversifiée d'un balkanisme, C. Chamoreau & L. Goury (eds), *Conséquences linguistiques du contact de langues et changements linguistiques. Tendances dans le domaine de la prédication*, Paris, CNRS éditions, 20 p.
- Adamou E., à paraître (2012), Change and variation in a trilingual setting. Evidentiality in Pomak (Slavic, Greece), I. Léglise & C. Chamoreau (eds), *The interplay of variation and change in contact settings: Morphosyntactic studies*, Amsterdam, Benjamins, 20 p.
- Adamou E., 2010, Deixis and temporal subordinators in Pomak (Slavic, Greece), In I. Bril (ed.), *Clause-Linking and Clause-Hierarchy: Syntax and Pragmatics*, Amsterdam/Philadelphia, Benjamins, p. 399-420.
- Adamou E. & G. Drettas, 2008, Slave, *Le patrimoine plurilingue de la Grèce Le nom des langues II*, E. Adamou (éd.), BCILL 121, Leuven, Peeters, p. 107-132.
- Adamou E., 2008, Arménien, *Le patrimoine plurilingue de la Grèce Le nom des langues II*, E. Adamou (éd.), BCILL 121, Leuven, Peeters, p. 71-76.
- Adamou E., 2006, Temps et espace en našta, *Rencontre du temps et de l'espace*, S. Naïm (éd.), Leuven, Peteers, p. 105-119.
- Adamou E., 2005, Typologie de la syntaxe connective en našta, *Typologie de la syntaxe connective,* C. Clairis, C. Chamoreau, D. Costaouec, F. Guérin (éds), Rennes, Presses universitaires de Rennes, p. 171-182.

7.5. Academic Journal Papers

Adamou E., 2011, Temporal uses of Definite Articles and Demonstratives in Pomak (Slavic, Greece), *Lingua* 121/5, p. 871-889.

- Adamou E., 2010, Bilingual Speech and Language Ecology in Greek Thrace: Romani and Pomak in contact with Turkish, *Language in Society* 39/2, p. 147–171.
- Adamou E. & D. Costaouec, 2010, Connective constructions in the world's languages: A functionalist approach, *La Linguistique* 46/1, Paris, PUF, p. 53-90.
- Adamou E., 2009, Le marquage différentiel de l'objet en nashta et en pomaque (Grèce). Retour sur l'hypothèse du contact, *Bulletin de la Société de Linguistique de Paris*, 104/1, p. 383-410.
- Adamou E., 2005, Du contexte sociolinguistique à l'exception dans deux grammaires du grec moderne, *Faits de langue*, «L'exception: entre les théories linguistiques et l'expérience », I. Poustovaïa (éd.), 23, Paris, Ophrys, p. 71-74.
- Adamou E., 2004, La personne en našta. Approche comparative avec le bulgare littéraire et le macédonien, *La Linguistique* 40, 2, Paris, PUF, p. 103-124.
- Adamou E., 2003, Le rôle de l'imaginaire linguistique dans la néologie scientifique à base grecque en français, *La Linguistique*, 39, 1, Paris, PUF, p. 99-110.
- Adamou E., 2002, De la stabilité de l'imaginaire linguistique, *Langage et société*, 99, Paris, Maison des Sciences de l'Homme, p. 77-95.

7.6. University Journal Papers

- Adamou E., 2005, Enquête sur la pratique du našta. Le cas de Liti (Grèce), *Education et sociétés plurilingues*, 18, Aoste, p. 77-88.
- Adamou E., 2005, Les noms de couleurs d'origine française en grec moderne, *Sêméion*, 2/3, Couleurs et signes, linguistique et sémiologie, p. 27-33.
- Adamou E., 2002, Représentations sur le lexique, *Revue des Lettres et de Traduction,* 8, Université Saint-Esprit de Kaslik, Liban, p. 411-420.

7.7. Publications in conference proceedings

- Breu W. & Adamou E., (in press), Slavische Varietäten in nichtslavophonen Ländern Europas. Das deutschfranzösische Gemeinschaftsprojekt *EuroSlav 2010* [Slavic varieties in non-Slavic speaking European coutries. The German-French project EuroSlav2010], *Wiener Slawistischer Almanach*, Muenchen, Sagner, 29 p.
- Adamou E., 2011, A temporal set of uses of the deictic suffixes in a Pomak variety, Greece, Pre-proceedings of the *11th International Balkan Conference*, ed. Makarcev M., Sedakova I., Civjan T., Institute for Slavic Studies, Russian Academy of Sciences, Moscou, 22-24 March 2011, 194-198.
- Arvaniti Amalia & Evangelia Adamou, 2011, Focus expression in Romani, Proceedings of the 28th *West Coast Conference on Formal Linguistics* (WCCFL 28), ed. Mary Byram Washburn et al., 240-248. Somerville, MA: Cascadilla Proceedings Project. www.lingref.com, document #2456.
- Adamou Evangelia & Amalia Arvaniti, 2010, Language-specific and universal patterns in narrow focus marking in Romani, *Speech Prosody 2010*, 11-14 May 2010, Chicago (USA), 100086: 1-4. http://speechprosody2010.illinois.edu/papers/100086.pdf
- Adamou E., 2008, Aux traces d'une dégrammaticalisation : le médiatif en pomaque (Grèce), *Revue des Etudes Slaves* 79/1-2, Pre-proceedings of the French Delegation to the 14th International Congress of Slavists, Ohrid 10-16 September 2008, p. 177-189.

- Adamou E., 2007, The *jimam* perfect in Nashta, *Bălgarckite octrobi na Balkanite*, P. Assenova et al. (eds), Proceedings of the *Bulgarian "islands" on the linguistic map of the Balkans*, Sofia University, 4-6 November 2005, Sofia, Figura, 87-94.
- Adamou E., 2007, Grammaticalisation du parfait avec *avoir* dans quelques variétés slaves de Grèce, Proceedings of the **29**^e **Colloque international de linguistique fonctionnelle**, Helsinki, Publications du Département des langues romanes de l'Université de Helsinki, p. 1-5.
- Adamou E., 2006, Traitement de l'aspect dans les emprunts verbaux du našta au grec, *Perspectives fonctionnelles : emprunts, économie et variation dans les langues*, Lopez Diaz, Montes Lopez (eds), Lugo, Axac, p. 141-143.
- Adamou E., 2004, Synchronie dynamique de la confixation, *Créoles, Langages et politiques linguistiques,* C. Feuillard (éd.), Proceedings of the **26**^e **Colloque international de linguistique fonctionnelle**, Guadeloupe, 30 sept. 7 oct. 2002, Berne, Peter Lang, p. 215-219.
- Adamou E., 2002, Peut-on prévoir la dynamique lexicale?, *L'Imaginaire linguistique*, A.-M. Houdebine (éd.), Proceedings of the *Colloque International Imaginaire linguistique*, Paris, 30 Nov. 1 Dec. 2001, Paris, L'Harmattan, p. 31-36.
- Adamou E., 2002, La graphie, indice de mots d'origine grecque en français contemporain?, *Recherches en linguistique grecque*, C. Clairis (éd.), 2 vol., Proceedings of the *5th International Conference on Greek Linguistics*, Paris, September 2001, Paris, L'Harmattan, vol. 1, p. 35-38.
- Adamou E., 2002, L'opacité sémantique des lexèmes d'origine grecque dans le français contemporain, La linguistique fonctionnelle au tournant du siècle, C. Tatilon et A. Baudot (éds), Proceedings of the **24**th **International Conference of Functional Linguistics**, Toronto, 23-27 juin 2000, Toronto, Editions du GREF, p. 13-17.
- Adamou E., 2001, L'Imaginaire linguistique des mots d'origine grecque en français contemporain (en grec), Proceedings of the **21**st **Conference of the Department of linguistics of Aristotle University**, Salonica, 12-14 mai 2000, Aristotle University Press, p. 1-8.

7.8. Conferences in International Congresses without proceedings

1. Peer-reviewed

- sep 2011, E. Adamou, A preliminary study of Romani in Mexico, *Gupsy Lore Society Meeting 2011*, 1-3 September, Graz [Oral].
- sep 2011, S. Gryllia, A. Arvaniti, M. Baltazani, E. Adamou, M. Terkourafi, N. Vergis, S. Tsiplakou, On the perception of varieties of Greek. Results from a perception- and a rating-experiment, *10th International Conference on Greek Linguistics* (*10th ICGL*), 1-4 September 2011, Democritus University of Thrace [Oral presentation by Arvaniti & Baltazani].
- juin 2011, S. Tsiplakou, A. Arvaniti, M. Baltazani, E. Adamou, S. Gryllia, M. Terkourafi, C. Themistocleous, N. Vergis, S. Armosti, Intonational variation in polar and wh- questions across seven varieties of Greek, *6th International Conference on Language Variation in Europe* (ICLaVE 6), 29 June-1 July, Freiburg [Oral presentation by Adamou & Themistocleous].
- juin 2011, S. Gryllia, A. Arvaniti, M. Baltazani, E. Adamou, M. Terkourafi, N. Vergis, S. Tsiplakou, On the perception of varieties of Greek. Results from a perception- and a rating-experiment, *6th International Conference on Language Variation in Europe* (ICLaVE 6), 29 June-1 July, Freiburg [Poster session].

- sept 2010, E. Adamou & A. Arvaniti, Prosodic, morphological and syntactic focus marking in Komotini Romani, *9th International Conference on Romani Linguistics*, 2-4 September 2010, Helsinki. [Oral presentation by E. Adamou].
- sept 2010, E. Adamou, Screening of the short film *Sabiha* With an introduction on the Muslim Roma trilingual community of Xanthi (Greece), *9th International Conference on Romani Linguistics*, 2-4 September 2010, Helsinki. [Oral presentation by E. Adamou].
- janv 2010, Evangelia Adamou & Amalia Arvaniti, Focus expression in Romani, **84th Annual Meeting of the Linguistic Society of America** (LSA), 7-10 January 2010, Baltimore-USA [Oral presentation by A. Arvaniti].
- oct 2009, Romani-Turkish-Greek trilingualism in Thrace (Greece). Followed by the short film *Sabiha*. *9th International Conference on Greek Linguistics* (9th ICGL), 29-31 October 2009, University of Chicago [Oral].
- juil 2009, Denis Costaouec & Evangelia Adamou, A typology of connective (copula) constructions, *Association for Linguistic Typology 8th International Congress (ALT 8)*, 23-26 July 2009, University of California-Berkeley [Poster session].
- avril 2008, Panel book on E. Adamou's (ed) *Le patrimoine plurilingue de la Grèce*, Communication orale au **13th Annual World Convention of the Association for the Study of Nationalities**, Nation, Identity, Conflict and the State, Columbia University, New York, 10-12 April 2008.
- sept 2007, E. Adamou, M. Dunham, S. Robert, F. Rose and M. Vanhove, Exploring Prosodic Parameters for a Typology of Conditional and Temporal Clauses. *Association for Linguistic Typology 7th International Congress (ALT 7)*, Paris, 25-28 September 2007 [Oral presentation by E. Adamou].
- sept 2006, Evangelia Adamou & Martine Vanhove, What does prosody tell us about syntax? **Second Conference on the Syntax of the World's Languages** (SWL2), Lancaster, 14-17 September 2006
 [Oral presentation by M. Vanhove].

 RESUME: On examine le rôle de la prosodie dans les subordonnées temporelles et conditionnelles.

2. Following invitation

- mai 2011, Multilingual communities in Greek Thrace, *Updating the Sociology of Language in the Balkans* [org. J. Lindstedt], Finnish Institute in Athens, 10-12 May 2011 [keynote speaker].
- mai 2011, Screening of the short film 'Sabiha: Portrait of a Muslim Rom woman living in Thrace', *Updating the Sociology of Language in the Balkans* [org. J. Lindstedt], Finnish Institute in Athens, 10-12 May 2011.
- janv 2011, Ditropic Cliticization in Ixcatec, *Meso-American Inflectional Morphology Workshop*, [org. J.-L. Léonard], University Paris 3, 31 January-1 February 2011. [Oral]
- oct 2009, Multilingual inheritance in Greece: focus on Thrace. Followed by the short film *Sabiha*. *Discussion on minority language issues in Greece*. Joined event of the *9th International Conference on Greek Linguistics*, Pre-Workshop session Teaching Greek as a second language, [org. M. Terkourafi], 27 October 2009, University of Illinois-Urbana. [Oral]
- oct 2009, Verb morphologies in contact: Evidence from South Slavic (Nashta and Pomak) and Romani (Komotini) in Greece, *Morphologies in Contact*, [org. T. Stolz], 1st-3rd October 2009, University of Bremen/Germany [Oral].
- oct 2009, Adamou E., Jacquesson F., Merlan F., Taine-Cheikh C., Aperçu sur les langues des régions désertiques, Workshop *Déserts. Y a-t-il des corrélations entre l'écosystème et le changement linguistique ?* [org. C. Taine-Cheikh, E. Adamou et F. Jacquesson], Lacito CNRS, Villejuif (France), 19 October 2009 [Oral].

- mars 2009, Le marquage différentiel de l'objet en fonction de l'humanitude en nashta (slave, Grèce), Journée d'études *Saillance*, [org. N. Tersis], CELIA, Villejuif, 26 March 2009 [Oral].
- mars 2009, Discussing the language contact hypothesis: On the *na* direct object marking in South Slavic, *38th International Conference on Philologies, Section "Balkan linguistics"* [org. A. Rusakov], St. Petersburg State University, 11-20 March 2009 [Oral].
- oct 2008, Contact de langues et écologie : le romani et le pomaque au contact du turc (Thrace, Grèce), International Workshop *Ecology and Language Evolution*, [org. E. Adamou, F. Jacquesson & C. Taine-Cheikh], Paris-Lacito, 23 October 2008 [Oral].

8. Language documentation

- In Archive-Lacito http://lacito.vjf.cnrs.fr and Centre de ressources pour la description de l'oral (CRDO) of the CNRS.
- Annotated Romani (Greek Thrace) texts with API transcription, glosses and indication of loan words, translated in English.
- 2008, The Louse and the Rom, tale in Romani from Anahoma, Komotini, Greece. 8 minutes.
- 2008, The Coward and the Giants, tale in Romani from Anahoma, Komotini, Greece. 9 minutes.
- 2008, *The Man-Snake*, tale in Romani from Anahoma, Komotini, Greece. 3.50 minutes.